<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Aloisia, or, The amours of Octavia Englished ; to which is adjoyned The history of Madam du Tillait, both displaying the subtilties of the fair sex.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1681</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 95 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 60 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A25194</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A2897A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R9304</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11659251</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11659251</idno>
            <idno type="VID">48012</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A25194)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 48012)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 5:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Aloisia, or, The amours of Octavia Englished ; to which is adjoyned The history of Madam du Tillait, both displaying the subtilties of the fair sex.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12], 107 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Jacob Tonson ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1681.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Newberry Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Octavia, --  consort of Nero, Emperor of Rome, ca. 42-62.</term>
               <term>Du Thillay, Elizabeth.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Greg Schutz</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Greg Schutz</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:48012:1"/>
            <p>Aloiſia, OR, THE AMOURS OF OCTAVIA <hi>Engliſhed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To which is adjoyned the Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of Madam <hi>du Tillait,</hi> both diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>playing the Subtilties of the Fair Sex.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Jacob Tonſon,</hi> at the <hi>Judges Head</hi> in <hi>Chancery-Lane,</hi> near <hi>Fleet-Street,</hi> 1681.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:48012:2"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>WE must confeſs Love is of ſo ſubtle and ingeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous a Nature, that it eaſily finds ways to effect its Ends, when it has any De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign of rendring it ſelf Maſter of any Heart. In effect we ſee very few eſcape, upon whom it hath made any Enterpriſe, which it ſeldom does unleſs certain be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb facs="tcp:48012:3"/>of Victory; they who reſiſt and lay any Obstacle in its way, being thoſe who commonly feel the effects of it moſt violently.</p>
            <p>There are in the World two ſorts of People who displeaſe me most of all; the first of them are Painters, who not having been skil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful enough to invent or to compoſe Colours lively enough, wherewith to draw Eyes for <hi>Cupid,</hi> have taken a Phancy to repreſent him blind to us, and they value them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves for giving occaſion to a common, but falſe Proverb, that
<pb facs="tcp:48012:3"/>
               <hi>Love is blind.</hi> It ſeems to me more reaſonable to ſay, that the Cloth with which they blindfold him, ſerves rather for a covering for their Ignorance, ſince with all their Endeavours they have not been able to make Eyes for any Deity, which could come near the Vivacity, Splendour, or <hi>Eclat,</hi> with which his ought to appear. For if (as the Ignorant would perſwade us) he did not ſee at all; how could he have ſubjected to himſelf ſo many as live now un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his Laws; could he without
<pb facs="tcp:48012:4"/>Eyes have enlarged his Empire over the whole Earth? We ſee his Conquests are without Number or Bounds; beſides I know that where he would inſinuate himſelf, he makes greateſt uſe of the Eyes of one Object to inflame another, which he would not do, did he not know that the Eyes were of all the Senſes the moſt ſuſceptible, becauſe they are the first, which diſcover. There muſt be know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of it in him, this Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge cannot be acquired without Study, and what means are there
<pb facs="tcp:48012:4"/>for one blind to become Learned, when the most neceſſary of Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties, the ſight fails him. It cannot be denied notwithſtanding, but that <hi>Cupid</hi> is learned, ſince we ſee by dayly experience that he confounds the moſt ſolid of Reaſons, and that no body can enter into diſpute with him with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out being certain to be worſted. It is juſt therefore to defend him from the wrong which is en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured to be done to him by taking away the chiefeſt of his Ornaments.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:48012:5"/>
            <p>The ſeeond ſort of men I hate, are a ſort of particular per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons who make a neceſsity of what is mere accident: I mean thoſe People who will have it to be an infallible thing, that Fortune is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſeen in the ſame place with deſert. I know very well that they dwell rarely in the ſame ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject. But in fine it is ill, to think to take that for indispenſably ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary, which is only the effect of Chance. It is true, that one hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pens much oftner than the other, for we ſee ſome to whom the
<pb facs="tcp:48012:5"/>name of Merit, has, not had ſo much as acceſs, toward whom notwithſtanding Fortune has been laviſh; and on the contrary, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers who have merited all things yet have had nothing. But after all, there are to be found, thoſe who poſſeſs both, there being this difference between them, that thoſe who have merit, find within themſelves content. For a man of ſenſe ought to conſider that it is more honourable not to have what one deſerves, than to poſſeſs what one does not deſerve; and it is
<pb facs="tcp:48012:6"/>in this manner that he enjoys all things, and in far a more noble manner, when he even wants eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thing; whereas he who has eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thing he wiſhes for, enjoys no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing unleſs he enjoy himſelf, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe it being but an imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary or viſionary Poſſeſsion, whereof he never taſts the true good, being naturally unworthy of it. As for thoſe who have both, we may ſay, if they have more happineſs, it is only with the Vulgar, ſince as I have ſaid For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune contributes nothing to the fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licity
<pb facs="tcp:48012:6"/>of a great Courage, and he ought to borrow from none but him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to make himſelf truly happy; I come back to my Theam, and advance to convince thoſe viſibly whom I have undertaken, that there are ſeveral who have extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary Merits to whom Fortune hath alſo been favourable, which the following Relation will not a little Illuſtrate.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="aloisia" type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:48012:7"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:48012:7"/>
            <head>ALOISIA: OR, The Amours OF OCTAVIA.</head>
            <p>THe eaſie Humour of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Husbands, and the freedom of Acceſs to be had with an infinite number of fine Women, rendred <hi>Paris</hi> one of the moſt polliſht and agreeable Cities of the World. It was but being of an Amorous Temper, and a man was certain to lead a happy Life, and if in the beginning any Lover happened to
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:48012:8"/>be croſſed in his Paſſion, his Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſs would be ſure not to leave him any longer in his Affliction than it was neceſſary to make him have the more relliſh of the ſweet of being beloved; The greateſt Beauties did not ſcorn this Artifice of ingaging their Gallants faſter to them; <hi>Octavia</hi> alone was Enemy to all theſe little Amorous tricks, confeſſing ingenuouſly that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing was ſo troubleſome to her as a Lover who was three days without declaring his Paſſion, and to whom ſhe ſhould be forced to make the advances; for ſhe loved to have him free and open, never to hide any thing from her, not even his weakneſſes, and if he felt any Amorous motion ſtirred up by her he ſhould let her know it in the ſame moment. But before I ſpeak of the Amours of this free hearted Lady, let me deſcribe her
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:48012:8"/>Perſon to you. The ſhape of her Face is an irregular Oval, her Eyes are gray, and her look with them very laſcivious, her Mouth too wide, but of a fine colour, her Forehead little, her Noſe long and lean, her Chin picked, her Teeth very white, her Hands dry, hard and ugly, upon which one may diſcover the leaſt Vein, her Hair is of a cheſnut colour, and curled in great Curls, and her Complexion ſmooth, and ſometimes very good; ſhe is for ſhape little, and Arched, and the many ſhocks her body has endured makes it have no firm Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuation, it balancing from one ſide to the other upon her Hips; as for the skin of her Neck and her Breaſts it is incomparable, and it may be very well ſaid of her that ſhe hides what is fineſt about her, and that happy are her Lovers who have liberty to ſee all her
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:48012:9"/>Beauties. Yet I have often heard them complain, that in the leaſt heat this fine Body ſends forth a ſmell, which is not ſo pleaſing to the Noſe, as the Body is to the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Senſes; She always takes great care to have her Shoes and Stockings well put on, the Silk ſtockings ſhe wears are always drawn up half way her Thigh, and her Garters are very neatly tyed; no Woman takes ſo much care to carry her Feet well as ſhe; As for her Mind, ſhe has a great deal of Life, but little Judgment, and very wild, her Humour is haughty, jilting, malitious, and jealous, ſhe is not able to endure the Careſſes are made to other Women (as if ſhe had where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withal to content all Mankind:) It is enough to be handſom to be her Enemy, ſhe ſpeaks continually ill of the prettieſt, and invents all
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:48012:9"/>ways poſſible to give ill Impreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of them; She has no ſmall kindneſs for Money, and the moſt beloved of her Gallants are not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways the handſomeſt, nor thoſe who have moſt Merit, but the greateſt liberallity; and if there happen to be any one that does not leave ſometimes upon her Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble a Looking Glaſs, a Necklace of Pearl, or ſome other fine thing, he is looked upon with leſs tenderneſs than the others.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Octavia,</hi> although ſuch a one as I have deſcribed, at her firſt begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to receive Company, or her firſt Entrance into the World, had notwithſtanding, a great crowd of Adorers, and ſome of the chiefeſt and hanſomeſt of the young men of <hi>Paris</hi> (where ſhe then lived) who were ſo well mannaged by her, that ſhe did not looſe one; But <hi>Cleander</hi> was moſt kindly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:48012:10"/>and moſt loved by her, this Lover by the officious care he had of giving her often changes of Trimmings, had made a won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful progreſs in her heart, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides he was not the worſt made in the World, his ſhape was very neat and well ſet, his meen very paſſable, but his Complexion ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding ſwarthy, his Eyes rough, his Mouth big, and wide from Ear to Ear, a great quantity of Hair curled in large Curles, he was wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, quick, undertaking and capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of great things; a little too much a bragger, and one of thoſe Huffs, who think one muſt be bru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh, and paſſionate, and quarrel every one he meets, to be thought a man of Courage, his moſt vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Paſſion is for Women, and he gives himſelf wholly up to them: This did not a little haſten the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecting his Deſign upon the heart
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:48012:10"/>of <hi>Octavia,</hi> he obtained an abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of ſmall favours from her, and received all the ſigns of a ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Paſſion: but he having no thoughts of Marriage, valued only the ſolid pleaſures of Love; One day he went and finding her alone, after having made ſome Preſent according to his Cuſtom, he knelt down upon the ground with one Knee, and taking her hand, he kiſſed it ſeveral times, and ſpoke thus to her: <hi>You tell me you love me better than all Mankind beſides; but what ſigns have you ever given me of this tender Friendſhip, that can make me think my ſelf happier than any other of my Rivals? They ſee you as well as I, they have your leave to diſcover their paſſions to you, they ſigh in your preſence, and in fine I cannot make one ſtep be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you which I do not ſee them i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitate. You would notwithſtanding
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:48012:11"/>have me perſwade my ſelf by an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicite Faith, that I am happier in your heart than they are; Oh Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam, Madam, do not diſſemble; Had you that Love for me which you pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend, you would eaſily have made me (before this time) ſenſible of it by more preſſing and ſtronger proofs. Nature is not ſo unkind to the fair, as not to have endowed them with ſtronger Links, whereby to keep their Priſoner longer in their Chains; ſhe has diſtributed amongſt them ineſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mable Treaſures with which they may reward Conſtancy and Fidelity. Theſe are the moſt ſolid Evidences by which you can let me know the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference you make between other men and my ſelf; you may very well think my Diſcretion will never ſuffer ſuch a Secret to come out of my Mouth, and that I would rather have my life torn from me than diſcover it;</hi> in concluding his Diſcourſe, he ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tured
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:48012:11"/>with the greateſt amorous Tranſport imaginable, to ſlip up his hand towards that place, which it is more natural to touch, than modeſt to name. Hold, hold, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied <hi>Octavia</hi> (giving him ſuch a manner of repulſe, that he perceiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſhe was not much diſobliged by his way of proceeding) you go on ſtrangely faſt, and do not conſider the ill effects which would follow: If I ſhould condeſcend to what you would have me, to what a mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable condition ſhould I be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duc'd, if by the ſhameful and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt inevitable Effects, what I had done for you ſhould come to be known? All the World would look me out of countenance, and I ſhould after ſuch an Infamy be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the ſcorn of thoſe who at preſent ſeek after me with a vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Paſſion, for Marriage. I know very well Honour is but a Whim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zy,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:48012:12"/>a fine Phancy which has been invented to keep thoſe of our Sex within the bounds of duty; but they are ſuch Phancyes (though perfectly Viſionary) as we are ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged to run after for ſome time if we will live happy. When we are ingaged in Marriage, our ſhame is then leſs becauſe it has more ſharers, we have then liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to do what we pleaſe, ſince we have a Cloak to cover all diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders; and having no witneſſes, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is ſpoken but by weak Gueſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, wherefore we can then look upon what ever can be ſaid of it, as only Malice and Lies; It will be in that time that we ſhall live hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py (my Dear <hi>Cleander</hi>) and that by a wonderful Art we ſhall unite more ſtrongly our Souls and Hearts. <hi>Schelicon</hi> the Doctour you know (to whom without doubt by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of his great ſtupidity I ſhall be
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:48012:12"/>able to give what fold I pleaſe) vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſits me very often, ſhewing the greateſt eagerneſs poſſible to mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry me, and his Fortune is too con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable to be refuſed. This makes me humour him that I may be the ſooner his Wife, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently have the more liberty to be yours. What Madam, replied <hi>Cleander,</hi> do you intend to come ſoiled with the kiſſes of a ſtupid Brute, and offer me the reliques of his brutiſhneſs; can you want wit to that degree as to ſuffer ſuch an Original to gather the firſt Flowers of your Youth and of your Love? and will you prefer him before me?</p>
            <p>No, no, replied <hi>Octavia,</hi> I know very well what difference to make between him and you, and I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe you that I will give you a randezvous, when the Marriage is juſt upon the point of concluding,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:48012:13"/>which ſhall aſſure you of my Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon as well as my Heart. <hi>Cleander</hi> preſſed her extremely upon the ſame Subject all the remaining time of their Converſation, and told her that he had admirable Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceits to prevent the evil ſhe fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: but all he could ſay was un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſucceſsful, and he was forced at laſt to build all his hopes upon the promiſes ſhe had made to him.</p>
            <p>She after this Adventure dealt ſo cunningly with <hi>Schelicon,</hi> and got his eſteem and heart ſo wittily, that he thought the happineſs of his Life depended upon marrying ſo fine and ſo vertuous a Maid, and thought he ought not to loſe one moment in haſtning to poſſeſs ſo great a Treaſure; he met with no great Obſtacle, for her Parents who knew her to be of a wild and giddy Inclination, were glad to be diſcharged of her into the hands
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:48012:13"/>of the Doctour, and were eaſily brought to conſent to have it ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhed in few days. The hearing of this good News did not a little rejoyce <hi>Octavia,</hi> her mind being ſo pleaſed with it, that ſhe could not contain from giving <hi>Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander</hi> notice of it by the following Letter.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <head>
                     <hi>Octavia</hi> to <hi>Cleander.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>SChelicon <hi>is to marry me very ſuddainly: but Juſt Heaven, how little reaſonable are we to ingage our ſelves to do any thing. I trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, my Dear, when I think you ſhould remember what I have pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed to you. I muſt confeſs to you ingenuouſly, that if I were ſo unhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py as to ſee you, late this Night in my Chamber, ſummoning me accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:48012:14"/>to my promiſe, I am ſo ſtrict an obſerver of my Word, that I ſhould without doubt grant you what I have promiſed: I conjure you therefore do not come, and I ſhall always own that obligation to you which you will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve by it.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Octavia.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>
               <hi>Cleander</hi> eaſily underſtood the meaning of the Letter, and ſoon perceived his Miſtreſs would that Night crown his Wiſhes: ſo that without giving any Anſwer, he ſtayed with ſuch an impatience, as ſuch a Lover as he muſt needs have, expecting the coming of happy Night, that by means of its darkneſs he might go into her Lodgings unperceived. He was skilful in theſe Affairs, and found out his time ſo well that he per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed what he had deſigned, and
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:48012:14"/>found her alone in her Chamber; he loſt no time having ſo fair an opportunity, and by a thouſand lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle freedoms he took, he wakened in her heart a ſecret motion which made her change colour ſeveral times: he follows his Point, takes his advantages of her weakneſs, and looſed to Action ſome thing more powerful, which ſhe could not reſiſt, and this Amorous Lady found her ſelf at laſt forced to yield up her Arms and Life in a ſweet Amorous Languiſhment to her Conquerour; ſhe came often again to hand with him, and as long as <hi>Cleander</hi> had any vigour or ſtrength left, this Combate was continued; ſhe never ceaſed, ſaying all Night long, that Man was a ſtrangely well contrived Creature, and that ſhe ſaw nothing in the World which equall'd him in Merit; ſhe did nothing but contemplate with
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:48012:15"/>the greateſt curioſity what Nature had endowed him with more than her, and foundin him nothing but Subjects of Admiration &amp; Pleaſure; the Joy which ſhe had received in all the Attacks which her Lover had performed with ſuch Honour, made her ſollicite ſtill for more, ſhe ſeeming to gather new ſtrength by the failure of his; It was not ſo with poor <hi>Cleander,</hi> he was per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly exhauſted, and his ſtrength failed him, he was willing to enter the Liſts again, but a Law of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture full of cruelty forbad him to proceed: which <hi>Octavia</hi> obſerving, and expecting no further ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction from him, ſhe had him con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducted out of her Lodgings with the leaſt noiſe and moſt ſecrecy ſhe could; as ſoon as day began to appear, ſhe went afterwards to Bed, where ſhe remained all that day, pretending to have ſome ſlight
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:48012:15"/>Indiſpoſition upon her.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Schelicon</hi> made appear all the weakneſs of a tranſported Lover, when he learnt the news of this pretended ſickneſs, he cried and howled in the hideouſeſt manner in the World, and ſtamping with his feet againſt the Ground, he lifted his Eyes to Heaven in ſo diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>agreeable and ſo fantaſtical a way, that far from moving any that ſaw him, it was impoſſible for them to keep from laughing. No matter were he ten times a greater block<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head, he is wiſht for for a Husband, and if he know what it is not to be a burthen to a Wife all Night, he ſhall be received with open Arms, without being inquired in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to for any thing elſe; <hi>Octavia</hi> has a mind to be ſatisfied in that Point, and know what he is worth; for this reaſon ſhe re-aſſumes her for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer health, and puts her ſelf into
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:48012:16"/>a condition to receive him for a Husband on the day appointed. The Marriage being accompliſhed, both ſtay only for the pleaſures that expected them at Night, not giving any heed at all to any Day-Diverſions.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Octavia</hi> by an affected bluſh counterfeits the modeſt ſhamefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced Maid, and ſays ſhe had rather die than paſs a Night with a Man, whilſt <hi>Schelicon</hi> puſhed on by his Paſſion alone ſeizes her with vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, and throwing himſelf brisk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly into her Arms, after having made her cry out ſome moments by reaſon of the pains ſhe preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to endure, rowling languiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Eyes, and loſing her Voyce, ſhe became unmoveable, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to ſwoon away. The poor Husband thinks her already dead, and fancies ſo tender an Age was not able to endure ſuch fierce At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tacks,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:48012:16"/>he does all he can to bring her out of the ſwoon: But Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar, and all he could put in her Mouth was not able to recover her; he thinks therefore to have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe to the Surgeon, and to that intent calls his Man, but ſhe in that moment ſeem'd to come to her ſelf, and recovering the uſe of her ſenſes, ſhe cries out to him (laying her hand negligently upon him) My Dear Heart, what a naughty man you are, you have made me endure more than ever I did in my Life before; he asked her par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, and ſeemed to be much trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, telling her that theſe were only the firſt Croſſes of a Married Life; but that ſhe ſhould have as much pleaſure hereafter, as ſhe had ſuffered pain now; ſhe was very well pleaſed with him the firſt Night, although one muſt be of a ſtrange taſte to relliſh him,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:48012:17"/>for he is very corpulent, of an ill ſhape, and abominably big, a great pretender to Jeſts, but without any Wit, all his pleaſure is to play up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Husbands for their jealous hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours. In his Face there appears nothing but ſtupidity and brutiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and whoſoever obſerves his Actions will find in them all the inſtinct of a Beaſt under the ſhape of a Man; he has a Heart which is little, baſe, and capable of all ſorts of weakneſs; but as for his Liver it lies bravely great, and all the reputation he has acquired, is to be accounted the greateſt Eater in the Country; he would have People think him a Learned Man, but thoſe who are well acquainted with him know that unleſs he had the Sciences by Infuſion he cannot have acquired any Knowledge in them, ſince he hath applied his Mind to nothing but the knowing
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:48012:17"/>when to diſcard an Ace in good time, whereby to get a Repicque; this may be ſaid to his advantage, that he is very open and reſerves no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to himſelf, things which are moſt private with others, are moſt publick with him. A Husband thus compoſed, was juſt ſuch an one as was fit for <hi>Octavia,</hi> he was not troubleſome, and when any Lover made her a Viſit, he (after having thanked him for the honour he did her) quitted the Room out of reſpect, and left him alone with his Wife. <hi>Cleander</hi> was one of the firſt who returned to ſtorming of the Place, after Marriage; it was the greateſt pleaſure in the World to him, to learn from her own Mouth the Art ſhe had uſed to perſwade her Husband ſhe had always lived vertuous and chaſt. He was ready to die with laugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing when ſhe related to him the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:48012:18"/>perplexity in which the poor Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band was by reaſon of her pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended ſwoon, the ingenious little troubles he had given himſelf to bring her to her ſelf again, and the zeal with which he had asked her pardon for hurting her; ſhe took care not to omit the leaſt Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance; and in fine in this and all the other Viſits her Gallant made to her, the Husband was always the Subject of their Mirth; ſhe giving <hi>Cleander</hi> reaſon enough to know by the many favours ſhe beſtowed upon him, that a Wife was much more obliging and eaſie than a Maid.</p>
            <p>In the happy Courſe of this Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luptuous Life, an unfortunate Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cident happened which diſturbed the pleaſures of theſe two Lovers. As <hi>Cleander</hi> one day was come to ſee <hi>Octavia,</hi> ſhe brought him into the Hall, where after having
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:48012:18"/>knocked at the door of her Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band's Cloſet, which was on one ſide of the Hall, and called him ſeveral times, without his anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing once (deſiring not to be inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted in ſome Affairs he was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout) ſhe begun to be more confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent within her ſelf, thinking for certain he was not within; ſo that in this great Liberty ſhe but very gently repulſed the pleaſing and ſtrong violences of her Lover, and the reſiſtance ſhe makes is only to re-inforce his Attacks; he ſighs, his Eyes ſeek hers, to foretel them the pleaſures they are juſt going to taſte, his Lips imprint a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Kiſſes upon her Mouth, and his Hands full of Fire, ſeize upon her and lay her down upon a Bench that was there. Then with the greateſt Tranſports of Love re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entred that Fort, where he had be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore found a kind Reception. In
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:48012:19"/>the midſt of his Joys he heard a Noiſe, and ſaw <hi>Schelicon</hi> coming out of the Cloſſet where <hi>Octavia</hi> had knocked; this hindering him from finiſhing what he had begun, he goes haſtily out of the Hall, and with ſo much precipitation, that he had not leiſure to take his Sword with him. <hi>Octavia</hi> in fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry immediatly, putting down her Coats, takes it up, and drawing it out of the Scabbard, preſents it to <hi>Schelicon</hi> with the Point towards her, ſpeaking to him in theſe Words: <hi>Pierce, Pierce, a thouſand times this Heart which another's Crime would have rendred guilty; and ſpare not a Miſerable Creature, which Heaven had choſen out to be the infamous object of the moſt horri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble beſtiality whereof Man was ever capable; I deſerve Death, ſince my fatal Beauty, and my Looks as inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent as they are, have been able to
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:48012:19"/>inſpire ſuch baſe and ſhameful thoughts, and I ought to ſhed my own blood to waſh another's Crime: But if I may be permitted to ſay ſomething in Juſtification of my ſelf before I die: Know then that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though ſhe who has had the honour to be choſen for your Wife be unfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunate yet ſhe is innocent and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takes not at all in the fault of that infamous Fellow. I was ſitting down upon the Bench, and ſlept, when at my awaking I found my ſelf in the hands of inſolent</hi> Cleander: <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven is my witneſs, what were my thoughts, &amp; whether the painfulleſt of deaths, would not have been more wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come to me than this Infamy: I threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned him to cry out, I cry'd out, got looſe from him, knock'd at your door, call'd you to my help, endeavour'd to avoid his violence; and my Nails imprinted upon his Face the effects of my weak revenge. But all I could
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:48012:20"/>have done Alas, would have been to no purpoſe, had not you appeared to reſtore to me that honour which this baſe Fellow was raviſhing from me; But why do you delay (dear</hi> Schelicon) <hi>my Death, ſince it is the only cure of deſperate and generous hearts? Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge, Revenge, my Injuries upon</hi> Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander, <hi>I requeſt it of you before my Death, and ceaſe to oppoſe my De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns; that which the Sword has fail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of, I will obtain by Poiſon. I owe the loſs of my Life to my own reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: The Ladies of</hi> Paris <hi>can never think I will outlive this Diſgrace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In ending her Diſcourſe ſhe got hold of the Sword ſhe had given to <hi>Schelicon;</hi> and feigned an endeavour to ſtrike it into her Breaſt, but he ſnatched it away, ſpeaking thus to her; What are you about to do, Madam, do you think it well, to puniſh the Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent for the Crimes of an inſolent
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:48012:20"/>guilty Man? Is it to have either generous or reaſonable thoughts? Nay, do not you fear God's pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment upon you for it? Tell me, can you be guilty of the Crimes of another, when your pure Will detects and abhors it? There muſt be conſent to make a Crime, it is in him alone, and that pureneſs, which remains in the midſt of Corruptions is a ſacred Oyl which preſerves it ſelf in frail and impure Veſſels? What would you then be contented yet (re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied <hi>Octavia,</hi> ſhedding an abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of Tears) to allow ſo miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable a Creature, the Illuſtrious Name of your Wife, and can you receive her into your Arms, after having been held in thoſe of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſure you do not think ſeriouſly that a Wife whoſe thoughts are ſo noble and virtuous, can look upon you after this Diſgrace without
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:48012:21"/>dying of Melancholy?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Schelicon,</hi> after having wiped away her Tears, embraces her, and gives her a thouſand Kiſſes with a more paſſionate fury than ever, whether becauſe ſhe looked better than at other times, or for what o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther reaſon, I know not; he examins her, and asks her every little Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtance of what had happened: whether ſhe had felt any Titillati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and if <hi>Cleander</hi> had been in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Extaſie? She aſſures him he could not, by reaſon of the reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance ſhe made. By this Aſſurance he received, he concludes that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of his Copy-hold was touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and is ſo well ſatisfied, that em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bracing her in an Amorous Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port, he carries her upon a Bed: Oh! how can you love me, ſays ſhe, ſince you are ſo little ſenſible of what concerns my Honour. No, no, I cannot endure you, and
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:48012:21"/>I have conceived ſuch a horrour for all Mankind, after ſuch an Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>front, that I could almoſt revenge it upon you. <hi>Schelicon,</hi> without ſtaying to anſwer her, made ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing intercede in favour of his Love, which ſhe was never in her Life able to reſiſt, ſo that he finiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Work which was left im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfect by his Wife's Gallant. It is true ſhe behaved her ſelf ſo mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtly on this occaſion, that ſhe would not (do what he could) be perſwaded to let him ſee her na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked: She continually putting down her Petticoats, ſaying, that it was againſt the Rules either of Honour or Good Manners for a Wife to ſatisfie the luſtful looks of a Husband.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Cleander,</hi> who had heard from the next Chamber (where he had remained) what had paſſed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween <hi>Schelicon</hi> and his Wife,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:48012:22"/>tranſported with Fury, as ſhe came into the Room, not minding any thing, came up to her, holding this Diſcourſe to her: I am then, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam, that unhappy Victim, you have choſen to have ſacrificed to your infamous pleaſures; you muſt have had one, and you have made the Lot fall upon me; and by an unparallelled exceſs of cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty, you have made me the Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, the Judge, and the Executio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of my own Puniſhments, your Lips moiſt with my Kiſſes, your Eyes full of Amorous Looks, your Heart full of ſighs in my Favour, your Soul raiſed to a noble and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Temper; You go and caſt your ſelf in my preſence into the Arms of another, and after that I had kindled a Noble Fire in your Soul, you ſuffer it to be extinguiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the beaſtly and ſhameful Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braces of the vileſt and baſeſt
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:48012:22"/>Men. If you would but ſuſpend (anſwered ſhe) <hi>Cleander,</hi> your Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentments, I ſhould eaſily make you underſtand, that as it was you alone who kindled that Flame in my Heart, you alone quenched it; Is it not true that the Soul is ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible but of what the Imagination repreſents, and that ſince mine was filled in greateſt raviſhments of pleaſure, with your <hi>Idea,</hi> I may well ſay that for you I ſaw it raiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and for you I ſaw it die? Oh! replied <hi>Cleander,</hi> when one lends the Body, it is very hard to keep the Soul from following it, that Union being not to be broken without great Violence. Say ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, Madam, that you do not love <hi>Cleander,</hi> that you love only <hi>Man</hi> in him, and he will anſwer you, that if ever he has loved you, he deteſts that Love as the moſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy failing he was ever capable
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:48012:23"/>of in his Life, and that hereafter he will look upon you with as much Horrour and Scorn, as here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore you appeared to him to be aimable. Saying theſe Words, he went angrily out of the Chamber, not ſo much as vouchſafing to hear what <hi>Octavia</hi> had to ſay for her ſelf: She called him back ſeveral times, and made uſe of all the lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Arts with which ſhe uſed to calm the Fury of her Lovers, but without ſucceſs, for ſince that time he would never ſee nor hear of her, publiſhing all the ills he can of her; ſhe ſoon comforted her ſelf for the loſs of him, reflect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſhe could not receive any more of his Viſits without great hazard after what ſhe had ſaid to <hi>Schelicon</hi> of him: Beſides, he was not of late ſo liberal as he had been, want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing money often, but above all the ſweetneſs of variety was a perfect
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:48012:23"/>Cure. There was no long <hi>Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>regnum,</hi> ſhe quickly got another Gallant, who was in her opinion well worth <hi>Cleander:</hi> He did not indeed <hi>ſay</hi> ſo much, but he did much more; and the happy por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion which was diſtributed to him by Nature held the place both of Wit and Deſert. After him came another, and then another; and at laſt ſhe ordered matters ſo that ſhe did not let eſcape one young man of any Faſhion in <hi>Paris,</hi> without her being informed of his blind ſide, as well as his excellency: Yet this voluptuous Life of hers at laſt was publick to all the Town, either by their indiſcretion, or by the Satyrical Humour of <hi>Cleander.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In fine ſhe was now look'd upon only with ſhame &amp; ſcorn, and every little hypocritical Gilt, whoſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct was as little reaſonable as hers, did nothing but talk of her actions,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:48012:24"/>Rendezvous and Aſſignations, publiſhing with open mouth the diſorders of her Life, ſhe began to find ſhe had done enough at <hi>Paris,</hi> and that her Trade was good for nothing when it was profeſſed o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penly; ſo that ſhe prevailed with her Husband to leave it upon ſome falſe pretences, and out of ſome pretended domeſtick Conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, which he at length yielded to; not knowing what it was to contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict her will, he conſented there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to what ſhe had ſo long ſolici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for, and choſe <hi>Orleance</hi> for his place of Reſidence; ſhe preferred this Place before all others, becauſe ſhe had heard the young men were as fit for her turn there, as any where in the World.</p>
            <p>The very firſt day ſhe came in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to this City, ſhe endeavoured to take other meaſures than ſhe had at <hi>Paris,</hi> and reſolved to live after
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:48012:24"/>a different manner, thereby to gain a ſtock of Reputation and Eſteem, ſhe made at firſt an acquaintance with thoſe Ladies of the Place, which paſſed for the diſcreeteſt and moſt vertuous, and by her ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs and plyable temper, got the friendſhip of the moſt ſincere; ſhe counterfeited a ſeverity of vertue to admiration; and would never in any diſcourſe allow, that there could be in the world any Woman ſo criminal as to give the leaſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful freedom to a man, and maintained it to be an incredible thing; and pretended to be very much diſobliged if any thing was ſaid in her company liable to an ill conſtruction, and when ever a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſuch diſcourſe happened, ſhe would immediately leave the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany with ſo well ſeeming a ſtudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſence of the Affront, that the moſt cunning of her own Sex,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:48012:25"/>would take her to be in earneſt: She put this conſtraint upon her ſelf for ſome few days, but was ſoon tired with that way of living, and begun to make it known that ſomething leſs of Reputation and more of pleaſure was what ſhe truly deſired. There was not any man in <hi>Orleance</hi> that had yet ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventured to make an Addreſs to her, and her greateſt trouble now was the being reduced to ſo ſmall an Ordinary, which was the cauſe ſhe reſolved to follow her inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and ſeek a more happy life; her Glaſs ſhewed her the little Beauty ſhe had now remaining, and ſhe ſaw very plainly that her two laſt Children had made her looſe that ſplendour of youth ſhe before carried in her Complexion; and that lively caſt which was heretofore ſo eaſily perceived in her eyes; To repair theſe faults
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:48012:25"/>ſhe had recourſe to Paint, both white and red, ſo borrowing a Beauty which ſhe owed only to Art, and which had a greater ſhare in it than Nature. If ſhe had af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards any ſeverity in her hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour, it was only in Publick Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies, for when alone in an Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>core with a man of an Amorous Temper nothing was more tracta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; ſhe wanted only ſome Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon declaring himſelf in love with her to render her happy, that was enough, ſhe loved him already before hand, without knowing either his Name or Merit. He who firſt broke the Ice was a <hi>Monk,</hi> who had left the Habit, who with his little Managements in that Condition, had gotten up a ſmall Stock of Gold, which did not a little ſerve to advance his Affairs. The name of this Monk was <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thonine,</hi> he was tall and very ſlen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:48012:26"/>his head and eyes bow to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Ground ever ſince his <hi>Noviciate,</hi> his Face is long and nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, two large bones covered with a rivelled skin, make up the ſhape of his Cheeks, below which are two great hollow pits, his eyes are ſunk ſo far into his head, that the colour of them can ſcarce be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived; his Chin is picked, his Noſe hooked, and his Complexion of the deepeſt dark brown; Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to accompany well this Face, has, inſtead of hair, given him two great broad Ears which riſe up a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove his head and make a pleaſant Proſpect, he does not want Wit, and expreſſes himſelf pleaſantly enough, but is very vain and proud of his knowledge, cunning and cheating; he would be accounted a great Wit in Converſation, and with an affected voice ſpeaks very ridiculouſly. Although he is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:48012:26"/>uglier than I have deſcribed him; yet he found no difficulty in obtaining what he deſired of <hi>Octa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>via.</hi> That which is to be ſold, mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney always commands, the ways of looking after it are only difficult. The firſt time he ſaw her ſhe was walking upon the New Walks on the Town-walls, and perceiving him have his eyes fixed upon her, eaſily believed he was ſmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten; ſhe fixes her looks upon him with a ſtudied Languiſhment; and pretending to be ſurprized by his, bluſhed, and caſt down her eyes with ſo well an affected Modeſty, that it preſently ſerved to increaſe his Paſſion: Upon this weak Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jecture he was reſolved (though upon never ſo dear terms) to get her Acquaintance, and like a true experienced Monk, began with en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavouring to make a Friendſhip with her Husband. He ſoon found
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:48012:27"/>that all his pleaſure conſiſted in being whole days at his meals and play; and in theſe humoured him ſo well by treating him often, that <hi>Schelicon</hi> ſeemed never ſo well plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed as with <hi>Anthonine,</hi> and could not well enjoy a moments reſt without ſeeing him. The Vintage ſeaſon was now come, and every one went to reap the pleaſures of the Country: at that time <hi>Scheli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>con</hi> deſired <hi>Anthonine</hi> to go with him, this favoured his Love too much to be refuſed; ſo they went accordingly with <hi>Octavia</hi> to take the freſh Air in the Countrey: <hi>Anthonine</hi> was no ſooner arrived thither, but he reſolved to diſcover his Love to <hi>Octavia,</hi> and after hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing often failed in opportunity, one day, <hi>Schelicon</hi> being at dinner, he found her alone ſitting down in the ſhade in a great Walk of Trees; he was not wanting in ſo
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:48012:27"/>fair an opportunity to diſcover his Love to her; but then uttered all the tender and paſſionate things can be imagined to proceed from a Heart wholly poſſeſſed with Love; What he then ſaid had that effect on <hi>Octavia</hi> that ſhe gave him reaſon to hope all that he deſired: but he being of a haſty humour, would not ſtop here, he would know how far he might hope his happineſs ſhould extend; the knowledge he had of her avariti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Nature, put him upon wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting a Letter to her in theſe Terms.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <head>
                     <hi>Anthonine</hi> to <hi>Octavia.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>I <hi>Should think my Love like that of a Novice, Madam, If to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover my paſſion, I ſhould tell you of Sighs, Languiſhments and ſweet Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtractions;
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:48012:28"/>my Love is more Maſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>line than to concern it ſelf with theſe Childiſh Play-games; it loves ſolid Action, and is not in the leaſt moved by the languiſhing looks of thoſe Viſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Lovers, who taſt only the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of being loved, by ſtrength of Phancie: That Noble Fire which Love kindles in our hearts is not to be evaporated in languiſhing looks and tender ſighs only, Nature hath given another vent to it much plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſanter and more convenient. When a Woman is loved by one of theſe weak Lovers, ſhe muſt expect only Words, and the proteſtations of a Chimerical tenderneſs: It is treaſon with them but to name Money, and when any Female becomes Mercena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, they think her no longer fit to be beloved. As for me, I take another Courſe, and have not made Sighs my only Aim; my Purſe is freely at your Service; and if you will but
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:48012:28"/>give me an hour towards night, you ſhall ſee my Stock, and know what I can do for you.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Anthonine.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>She ſoon returned him this An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, ſlipping it into his Pocket whilſt he was at play with her Husband.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <p>
                     <hi>ALthough I do not well under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the meaning of your Letter, yet I think there is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in it very agreeable and ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal; if you will take the trouble to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain it to me after Supper, I will endeavour to find a way to diſcourſe with you in private.</hi>
                  </p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>The Letter which <hi>Anthonine</hi> had written was ſo unfortunate, that after <hi>Octavia</hi> had read it, it fell out of her Pocket when ſhe pull<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:48012:29"/>out her Handkerchief, and was found in the middle of the Room by <hi>Schelicon,</hi> who read it over, and ſeemed to be vexed at it. <hi>Octavia</hi> who had ſearched every where for it, without being able to find it, and ſeeing ſuch a Melancholy in his Looks, eaſily judged that it had fallen into his hands: ſo that ſhe was forced to uſe the utmoſt of her cunning; ſhe therefore comes near him, and ſtroaking his face with her hand; careſſing and kiſſing him, ſhe asks him the reaſon of his Melancholy, and without giving him time to anſwer, will you lay a wager (ſays ſhe) that I will make you laugh, if I relate to you the pleaſanteſt thing in the World which has lately happened unto me: I am much obliged to you Sir (added ſhe with a ſcornful ſmile) to ſuffer your Friends to ſend me Letters full of Impertinencies: See
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:48012:29"/>ſays ſhe, ſearching in her Pocket, pretending to look for this Letter of <hi>Anthonine</hi>'s) what has been written to me, after this who can be truſted? <hi>Anthonine</hi> that Body of Death, that riveled and fearful face, that lean Skeleton, to ſpeak to me of Love, and to endeavour to ſuborn my Vertue? You would never believe it; if the Letter I am going to let you have a ſight of, were not an undeniable proof. After having ſaid this, ſhe ſearch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es one Pocket, than the other, takes out every thing out of both, looks in her Gown, undoes her Train, and is impatient that ſhe cannot find it. Upon which <hi>Schelicon</hi>'s firſt ſuſpicion being baniſhed, he gives it to her without ſaying a word. What, ſays ſhe, are you in the Conſpiracy to laugh at me? and has he given you a Copy of? No, replied he, in a more gentle
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:48012:30"/>tone; It is the ſame you had loſt, as I underſtand, and which I have found in this Room. Well, then ſays ſhe, what ſay you to this? who would not have been cheated by this Hypocrite? who ſeems hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to dare to look upon a Woman; If you will be ruled by me, to pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh his Inſolence, we will bubble him. She then propoſed a way to be diverted by him, which was for her to ſuffer his Addreſſes, to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer them obligingly enough, to gives rendezvouzes, to receive his money upon fine hopes, and thus to cheat him. <hi>Schelicon</hi> truſting entirely to her vertue, and to all that ſhe had ſaid, conſented to whatſoever ſhe deſired, and to the end he might give them more li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty to begin that very Night their new Game, he went out of the Houſe after Supper, and walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed abroad alone. <hi>Anthonine</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:48012:30"/>this bleſſed opportunity, thought he had diſcovered the happy minute; ſo that going into <hi>Octavia</hi>'s Bed-chamber, he found her lying upon the Bed, her Coats negligent &amp; diſorder'd, ſo great an effect had the ſeeing a Woman in this poſture upon him, that he was daſht, and not able to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach her. Am I ſo frightful (ſays ſhe, to him, perceiving his ill tim'd Modeſty) that you dare not endure the ſight of me, and are you only brave, with a Pen in your hand? Near ſo much Beauty (re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied <hi>Anthonine,</hi> coming to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>felf, and looking ſimply for his Purſe) how am I ſtricken with Admiration? and can a man offer you ſo little money as I have, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſome kind of trouble, to deſerve thoſe Favours, I hope to obtain from you? Lord! replied ſhe, taking his Purſe and looking ſted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſtly
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:48012:31"/>upon it, how fine is the hair with which this Purſe is made? are they yours? But what ſhall I do with it, added ſhe? take it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, I am not Mercenary: With theſe laſt words the Monk was ſo animated, that pulling up her coats with eagerneſs, he diſcovered her lovely Body naked: at the ſame time ſhe puts up the Purſe, not out of any ill deſign, having too good a Conſcience to keep the mony without giving him the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandize; ſhe ſhewed her Lover at this time, that ſhe had a great ſhare of Modeſty, turning her face upon the Bolſter, and ſhutting her eyes, pretending not to have the confidence to ſee her ſelf in ſuch a Poſture in the Arms of any man but her Husband. Then it was that <hi>Anthonine</hi> took poſſeſſion of what he ſo paſſionately wiſht for, and after having took ſatisfaction
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:48012:31"/>for his Purſe where with briskneſs then he came.</p>
            <p>The Husband being returned, <hi>Octavia</hi> makes to him a falſe Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of all that had paſſed, tells him of the Tranſports of <hi>Antho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nine,</hi> and calls him the Amorous Scheleton: confeſſes ſhe had felt ſome kind of horrour to ſee her ſelf alone with him; exaggerates the repulſes ſhe had given him, tells him ſhe would never ſuffer him to kiſs her hand, for fear a kiſs from ſuch a Satyr ſhould raiſe a bliſter; ſhews him the Purſe, ſwears to him he had given it to have one moment of Converſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with her: ſhe ſhares the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit with him; and by the relation ſhe makes of the ridiculous man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, with which he preſented it, makes <hi>Schelicon</hi> almoſt die with laughter: The good man laughs at the follies of a man, whoſe fool
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:48012:32"/>he really was. In fine, when ſhe was in bed ſhe embraced him more than ordinarily, to the end ſhe might make him believe ſhe drew water at no other Well but his.</p>
            <p>As long as <hi>Anthonine</hi> had Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney the Aſſignations were very frequent, and <hi>Schelicon</hi> uſed to go out of the Chamber and leave them together; but his Purſe fail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, it was time for him to think of returning to <hi>Paris</hi> to ſeek a new ſupply. <hi>Schelicon</hi> and <hi>Octavia</hi> ſoon followed him; and Vintage being done, they came up to Town to paſs the Winter there, and ſeek ſome other good fortune.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Octavia</hi> being at <hi>Paris</hi> thought it too little for her to be contented with her Monaſtick Ordinary, for change of meat quickens the Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petite. A certain Gentleman call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Caveceus,</hi> was the firſt who juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Anthonine</hi> out of favour, ſhe
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:48012:32"/>had too great a deſire to taſt of all conditions of men, not to receive a man of ſo good a <hi>Mine,</hi> and who came of one of the moſt Illuſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Families of that Place; ſhe would have one tryal at leaſt of him, let it coſt her never ſo much, that ſhe might mix Noble Blood with that of a Citizens: Such a good fortune was not to be refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by her, for he is finely ſhaped and very tall, but ſomewhat too ſlender; has good legs well ſhaped, and his hair is fair, well curled and frized, his mouth well made, his eyes pleaſant, a fine hand, his complexion is not very good, the Small Pox having left ſome marks; but as for his mind he is the moſt ſincere of men, ſweet, civil and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liging to all the World, he ſpeaks very ſlowly, and has ſome difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in expreſſing himſelf: But if any will hearken to him, they will find
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:48012:33"/>him ſay every thing very well and with great ſenſe; he pleaſes him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf extremely with Womens com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, and ſhews the Sex ſo great a reſpect, that he often by it becomes troubleſome, and chiefly to <hi>Octa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>via,</hi> whom he had almoſt made deſperate in the firſt converſations he had with her; ſhe who hates reſpect out of time, and who would have every one become fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliar immediately, was forced to endure him a long time without his ſo much as ſpeaking to her of his Love, or daring ſo much as to touch her hand; he thought to have done a great deal, and took himſelf to be a raſh Lover, if by chance he had fetched a ſigh, or caſt an amorous look in her pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence. From whence proceeds it, ſaid ſhe to him one day, (thereby to give him an opportunity to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover himſelf to her) that you
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:48012:33"/>ſeem to me to be ſo penſive and diſquieted, and that I phancy when ever I happen to obſerve you, you cannot be a moment without ſend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing forth ſighs? your languiſhing looks inſtruct me well enough, that your mind is wounded with ſome paſſion, tell me for God's ſake I requeſt it of you, (but without diſguiſing any thing) what cauſes this diſorder in you? I ſwear to you there is nothing in the World which I will not do to give you eaſe. To any other Perſon in the World beſides your ſelf, replied <hi>Caviceus</hi> (bluſhing and ſixing his eyes upon the ground) I would ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver grant <hi>(Madam)</hi> what you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire of me; but ſince I have vowed to reſpect you, and to obey you as long as I live, I will open to you all my ſecrets, and in ſome par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars ſhould be extremely am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitious of taking your Counſels.
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:48012:34"/>Know then Madam, a thing which I would never have told you, had you not commanded me, which is, that I love, and that with the greateſt violence, the moſt lovely Perſon that ever appeared under the Heavens, but as my love is very great, my profound reſpect is alſo ſo extreme, that I never have dared to tell her I ſuffered for her, and that I have hitherto rather choſen to be unhappy, than indiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creet: Tell me then Madam, is it not time for me to ſpeak at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent? have not I acted by ſighs on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, long enough? and may not I now make my complaints at the feet of her I love, of what torments ſhe has made me endure? her hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour is ſweet, her eyes tender and compaſſionate, her heart — What, interrupted <hi>Octavia,</hi> with Anger, thinking he had ſpoken of ſome body elſe; do you entertain
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:48012:34"/>me only with the Beauties of your Miſtreſs; your nature muſt be ſtrangely miſchievous, or at leaſt you very uncivil thus to praiſe her in my preſence; if you had not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly loſt your wits, certainly you would not have done thus, Oh! I had very well foreſeen Madam, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued <hi>Caviceus,</hi> that your vertue was too ſevere to ſuffer the confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion I have now made of that ſtrong paſſion I have for you; was it of me, replied <hi>Octavia</hi> (ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſtrangely ſurprized) that you ſpoke? Let us diſguiſe nothing, replied <hi>Caviceus,</hi> you have under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood it too well for my happineſs; well, if it be of me, replied <hi>Octa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>via,</hi> you may continue your Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, I will permit you; you go too much about, and ſpeak with too much obſcurity of a thing you would have known: Oh! Madam, replied he, if you did but know
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:48012:35"/>the purity of my deſires, you would never diſapprove of my Love, ſince it is wholly ſeperated from any thing of Crime; ſo that if you had leſs vertue you would ſeem leſs amiable to me. In fine he ſpent the reſt of this converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion only in exaggerating the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocency of his thoughts, although <hi>Octavia</hi> (if he had taken notice of what ſhe ſaid) required the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary of him, and that that was not the beſt quality ſhe hoped for, in a Lover. Another time as ſhe was with him, and being mighti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly concerned, that notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all the advances ſhe had made, there had no more paſſed betwixt them, ſhe was now reſolved to diſcover her thoughts to him up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this matter ſo clearly, that he ſhould be obliged indiſpenſably to proceed further; when one loves ſaid ſhe to him (with an affected
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:48012:35"/>baſhfulneſs) as much as you ſay, is one contented to do, ſo little as you do? Love then would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally have but very weak pleaſures if it ſhould proceed no further, and Perſons who love might with rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon complain to find themſelves ſo ill recompenced for the torments they are made to ſuffer under Love's Dominion. Well then, if it be ſo, replied <hi>Caviceus,</hi> why are you ſo unſenſible to the tenderneſs of a Heart which loves you ſo much? Alas! I know but too well your cruelty finds out this, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move me farther from you, and to force me not to love you, you pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend by this to repulſe my paſſion; by repreſenting to me the ſmall gains I ſhall receive from it; but in fine, why do you blame me, ſince thoſe weak pleaſures it feeds me with, have no ſenſual founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and nothing criminal in
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:48012:36"/>them? What other Foundation can a true Lover have for his plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, but the ſenſes, replied ſhe? the pleaſures, ſays he, of thinking of his Love, of entertaining him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf with little pleaſant diſquiets, to think of the Perſon he loves, to caſt towards her a thouſand amo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Looks, to complain, to ſigh, to languiſh and to weep: and do you call theſe (interrupted ſhe) the pleaſures of Love, truly you are a great Novice in it then, theſe are only the torments, and if you had a heart which were any ways touched with that paſſion, you would judge of the ſweets of it, by the violence of the torments you ſpeak of; I will let you know out of pity, where you will find the true and ſolid pleaſures of Love: you can (replied he) Madam, by loving me, and by that will render me happy beyond compariſon;
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:48012:36"/>As for what you now ask, you may be aſſured of, but—do not abuſe and inſult any more over (replied he, interrupting her very concernedly) the misfortunes of the miſerable, ſince it is you alone cauſes it, and if you have not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion enough to give me eaſe, at leaſt be not ſo cruel as to widen my wounds. They finiſhed this Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation as well as the others without coming to any Concluſion, and <hi>Octavia</hi> very much incenſed againſt her Gallant, was reſolved another time to demonſtrate to him what ſhe could not before make him underſtand, but ſhe not having the opportunity of ſeeing him often, her deſigns muſt have been delayed, had ſhe not invented a way how to facilitate their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce, and receive him more eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in her Chamber, which was to tell her Husband that if at any
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:48012:37"/>time ſhe ſuffered him in her Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, it was only out of Policy, he being a man of that Quality, and Great Intereſt at Court, that if there ſhould happen to them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny misfortune, he would be able to do them great Service; ſhe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon adviſed him to viſit him of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, to endeavour to gain his friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, and to accompany him in all his diverſions, telling him it would be the greateſt honour in the World for him, it being the only way to make him conſiderable in the World; He who never made uſe of any reaſon of his own, but ſuffered it to be always governed, followed her Counſel exactly, and was whole days with <hi>Caviceus,</hi> liv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing continually at his Table, which was always better ſerved than his own: <hi>Octavia</hi>'s true thoughts were, that thus adviſing her Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band to invite <hi>Caviceus</hi> often, ſhe
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:48012:37"/>ſhould be able, (knowing his ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liging humour, of giving her ſo often Preſents) in the abſence of her Husband to have him often with her in her Chamber, and might have the opportunity of paſſing many a pleaſant moment with him in her Alcore without ſuſpicion; All things ſucceeded to her liking better than ſhe expected: for <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viceus</hi> being grateful for the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours he had received from <hi>Scheli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>con,</hi> made offer to him of a Houſe of his to lodge in, which he accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of freely enough, and that gave <hi>Octavia</hi> better means of ſucceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in her deſigns; ſhe comple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented him often, and ſaid very obliging things to him upon his good <hi>Meen,</hi> ſhewed him her Neck and Breaſts naked, asking him what fault he found in them, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding all which her Linnen nor her Clothes were not any
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:48012:38"/>more rumpled or tumbled than at firſt; which tranſported her ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times to ſuch a degree as to make her almoſt quarrel with him open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; ſhe then ſhewed him a Song which blamed baſhful Lovers for ſighing, and tormenting them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves for a thing when almoſt of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer'd, they would not attempt get<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting poſſeſſion of, but he read it no better than he underſtood it. In fine one day, wearied with all the advances ſhe had made, ſhe was reſolved now to uſe the laſt reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, and had recourſe to demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration, to render that more ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible which ſhe had a mind to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover to him; ſhe knowing he was to come into her Chamber, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his Cuſtom after din<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, laid her ſelf upon the Bed in her Cornet, with her Breaſts naked, and her Petticoats ſo ill in order, that her Thighs
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:48012:38"/>might be ſeen; whilſt ſhe lay in this poſture pretending to ſleep, her Lover came alone into her Chamber (for ſhe had given order none ſhould give her notice of his coming, that he might find her thus) and ſeeing her in this unde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent poſture, bluſhed, and thought that by chance in her ſleep her Petticoats had flown up, ſo that he to hinder her from being in the Diſorder which, he thought, ſhe would be in, if ſhe awaked and found her ſelf in this Condition before him, takes up her Handker<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief, and with the leaſt noiſe he could for fear of waking her, co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers her Breaſts, and pulls down her Coats; in the ſame inſtant <hi>Octavia</hi> pretending to awake, puſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es him back with violence, ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thus to him, tell me perfidious fool, are theſe the Actions of a true Lover; ought not you to die with
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:48012:39"/>ſhame for your weakneſs? and does not it fill you with horrour, it being againſt the Order of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; I am (ſays he) it is true a Criminal, but it was Fortune cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the Crime; if you could but know the Innocency of my Thoughts, you would without doubt have a better opinion of me, ſince you would find me not guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the leaſt diſorderly motion: It is that Knowledge, replied the Lady, which makes me ſo much an Enemy to you, and makes me deteſt your Perſon: Madam, (re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied he, interrupting her) I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jure you to believe that what I did was only to ſpare you the trouble which you muſt have had to have ſeen your ſelf naked in my pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence; was it that way, anſwered ſhe, that you ought to have cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red it, and if you were but ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal, you would find out a better
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:48012:39"/>way to excuſe it. In fine, ſhe ſaid, all that could be ſaid, on ſuch an Occaſion, leaving him in that Wrath, that he went from her with the greateſt grief and ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row imaginable: This reſentment of <hi>Octavia</hi> did not laſt long; for <hi>Anthonine,</hi> came into her Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber in the ſame inſtant that <hi>Cavi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceus</hi> went out, and ſoon comforted her in performing for her what ſhe had in vain expected from the other too Modeſt Lover; ſhe ſpoke all the ill things imaginable of <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viceus,</hi> and aſſured him that ſhe had never conceived ſo much An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tipathy againſt any Man, as againſt him, and that if her Husband had not commanded her to receive him, ſhe would never have ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red him to come within her ſight: after this, ſhe ſet to work all the little engaging Endearments ſhe could, which ſucceeded ſo well,
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:48012:40"/>that ſhe got from him a very rich and pretty Suit of Knots: She took that day ſo much pleaſure in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving Preſents, that ſhe was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved to ask of <hi>Caviceus</hi> all the fine things ſhe had a mind to, ſince ſhe could get nothing elſe out of him, although when he came again to viſit her, he was received with all the accuſtomed kindneſs, as if nothing at all had happened; and the ſame day, ſeeing a Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond Ring upon his Finger, ſhe pretended to have a deſire to buy it, and commended it ſo that he could not handſomely refuſe giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it to her. When he went abroad, ſhe would always deſire him to buy things for her, which were al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways the beſt of the Kinds, he not being able to defend himſelf from executing her Orders, and as he was not kept within the narrow bounds of a ſmall Penſion, the leaſt
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:48012:40"/>of his Preſents was of greater va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue than three of <hi>Anthonine</hi>'s: It is true ſhe would have been unjuſt to have complained of the Monk, ſince he gave her all he had, and that to content her he had endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured all he could to content her. But as one day <hi>Anthonine</hi> was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone with her, repeating that plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure which he valued dear as his life: <hi>Caviceus</hi> was at the door re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned from the Exchange with an abundance of the moſt modiſh wearing things he could purchaſe for her; <hi>Octavia</hi> gave <hi>Anthonine</hi> only time to go out of the Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, and taking her Fann, ſhe en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured to abate the high co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour which the Exerciſe ſhe had juſt then uſed, had raiſed in her face. There could not be ſhewed more kindneſs to a man than ſhe did in this Interview, and fearing leſt by reaſon of the diſturbance
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:48012:41"/>ſhe ſeemed to be in, he might ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect ſomething; ſhe told him without asking, that <hi>Anthonine</hi> was juſt gone out; that her Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band was become jealous, and had deſired <hi>Anthonine,</hi> as his Friend, to have always an eye over her, and to obſerve her conduct; after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards in a pretended Confeſſion, which ſhe made to him, ſhe aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red him ſhe had the greateſt hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour in the World to be forced to be alone with ſuch a man, and that yet ſhe out of reſpect to her Husband had always ſuffered him to be in her company; <hi>Caviceus</hi> who believed all ſhe had ſaid to be true, began to offer her what he had then bought, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the reſt of the things, a Box ſet with Diamonds, wherein was his Picture; upon which <hi>Octavia</hi> taking the hand with which he preſented it, kiſſing it
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:48012:41"/>with great tranſport, and cried out; Oh God, how obliging and generous you are? why am not I able to do ſomething for you, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn for theſe favours? <hi>Caviceus</hi> felt a certain ſprightfulneſs in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf ſtirred up by this freedom ſhe had uſed, which emboldned him; he takes her hand and ſqueezes it between his, kiſſes it, faſtens his mouth full of fire to one of her breaſts, afterwards kiſſes her be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween them, then looks up into her face with ſome remainder of Modeſty, to know from her eyes whether his Actions pleaſed her, every thing flatters him, and he hears from her nothing but langui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing and amorous ſighs, he locks her in his Arms, and then fell ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerly to taſte thoſe Joys which he had ſo long deſired, and forborn out of a fooliſh Modeſty.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Octavia</hi> who had not dared ſay
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:48012:42"/>any thing for fear her Lover ſhould have uſed ſome other un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſonable reſpect, ſeeing he could not now draw back held this Diſcourſe to him not without con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinual Interruptions, puſhing him ſoftly back and raiſing him upon her Arms, ſeemed to be extreme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly concerned, and uttered all thoſe things we might expect from a cunning Girle (inſtructed by her Mother, and Aunt) on the Bridal Night, thereby to deceive the man into an opinion of his having obtained a Maidenhead. When ſhe found <hi>Caviceus</hi> retreating, ſhe fetching a great ſigh from the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom of her heart, and opening her Arms which ſhe let fall negligent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly upon the Bolſter, riſes from the Bed, and went to one ſide of the Chamber leaning her Head o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the Arms of a great Chair, her Hankerchief before her eyes,
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:48012:42"/>and pretending in this condition to fall out into Tears and Sobs, thereby the more to move <hi>Cavice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us,</hi> ſhe ſpoke thus to him with the moſt to be compaſſionated Tone of Voice in the World: Have I lived thus long, only, to ſee my ſelf ſhamefully in the Arms of any man beſides my Husband? and muſt I after having lived hitherto with ſo much Honour, be brought to ſee my ſelf the infamous Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of your Luſt? did Heaven give you all thoſe great Qualities, on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to ſeduce my Honour, and to diſturb the innocent pleaſures which a Citizen enjoyed with her Husband? Oh! miſerable Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, that I am, why had not I ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther choſen to die with the greateſt miſery of pains, then to expoſe my ſelf to thoſe torments, which at preſent are tearing my Soul? can I ever after this Infamy, be able to
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:48012:43"/>look upon my Husband, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive his innocent and chaſt Kiſſes, without dying of grief, to ſee that I have defiled by my unchaſtneſs, the purity of our Embraces? ſhe ſaid many other things which did ſo ſenſibly move <hi>Caviceus,</hi> that I do not know whether he did not for a moment repent of the Action he had performed: he uſed all his skill in comforting her, exaggera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the great number of Women who took the ſame Liberty, aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring her that all the fineſt Women of that City had the ſame ſweet ſin to anſwer for: but as the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure began to return, the counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feit Grief ceaſed, and inviting her to renew the Work, ſhe conſented to it, ſaying to him, that it was on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the firſt time that was dear, all the reſt coſting nothing, and that ſhe foreſaw, ſhe ſhould never be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to ſhake off the paſſion ſhe had
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:48012:43"/>now conceived for him; In fine for a concluſion, ſhe deſiring to take advantage of the abſence of her Husband obliged him to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main that Night with her, but ſcarce was this agreed upon, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore her Husband came in; all that ſhe could do, was to hide <hi>Caviceus</hi> in a Cloſet, and deſires him not to be impatient, ſince his arrival ſhould not hinder their Deſign, for he was accuſtomed after Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per to return to his Country houſe, a League from <hi>Orleans</hi> to lie there, not being able to diſpenſe with it, becauſe of ſome Domeſtick Affairs he had to diſpatch there, but the thing happened far otherwiſe than he had ſaid; for <hi>Schelicon</hi> being very weary, told her he could not return thither that Night, and that he comforted himſelf eaſily ſince he ſhould more agreeably paſs the Night with her. All that ſhe
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:48012:44"/>could do was to ſteal from her Husband one moment, and to go and give notice of this to <hi>Caviceus,</hi> ſhe cried out aloud to him from the door to be gone with the leaſt noiſe he could, and without ſtaying time enough to ſee him go, ſhe returns to the Chamber where her Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band was, to buſie him, that he might not take notice of the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out of <hi>Caviceus. Anthonine,</hi> who far from being gone away, when <hi>Octavia</hi> thought he was, out of a jealous humour had ſlipped behind the Hangings near that door, to ſee what paſſed between her and <hi>Caviceus:</hi> finding ſo fine an opportunity to revenge him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf of them both, goes out of the Chamber and ſhuts that door at the ſame time as <hi>Caviceus</hi> went to open that of the Cloſet where he was: but he hearing the noiſe of that door, ſtayed there, for fear of
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:48012:44"/>being ſeen, thinking it to be <hi>Octavia,</hi> who having changed her reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, had then ſhut it: So he ſtayed till Night, and ſeeing his Miſtreſs come into the Chamber with her Maid, he did not dare appear; he ſaw her undreſs her ſelf from the Cloſet, and ſaw her go into Bed, after having ordered the Maid to put out the Candle; when ſhe was thus gone into Bed alone he did not doubt but that her Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band was gone back to his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try-houſe, and thought that he had nothing to do but to prepare himſelf to lie by her; but finding himſelf not to be in the true con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition he ought to appear in, hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing exhauſted himſelf in the day time, he tarried yet ſome time in the Cloſſet repaſſing in his Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gination all the Objects which had before given him provocations, and feeling the firſt fore-runners of
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:48012:45"/>pleaſure, he comes out, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches her Bed, who ſleeping al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready, awaked at the leaſt noiſe he made, and taking him for her Husband, having as ſhe thought heard <hi>Caviceus</hi> go down, ſaid to him, Lord! what have you been doing ſo long? why did you not come to Bed, <hi>Caviceus</hi> being migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily moved at theſe reproaches, without giving himſelf the time to anſwer, undreſſes himſelf and caſts himſelf into her Arms, before ſhe found her miſtake. <hi>Schelicon</hi> hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing finiſhed his Letters comes into the Chamber with a Candle, and drawing the Curtains of the Bed, ſees <hi>Caviceus</hi> ſo advantagiouſly placed: I leave you to judge the amazement of all three; <hi>Octavia</hi> to find her Husband in two places, <hi>Caviceus</hi> to ſee him ſo near him, and <hi>Schelicon</hi> to ſee his Wife in the Arms of another. In fine, after
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:48012:45"/>this firſt ſurpriſal, <hi>Caviceus</hi> was forced to compound; and the Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles were, that he ſhould give a good Sum of Money to <hi>Schelicon,</hi> and the Freedom of his Table, and that <hi>Sehelicon</hi> ſhould let him have the uſe of the Place, of which he only reſerved the Propriety. The Treaty is yet in force, and they live all three in the greateſt Union imaginable.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div n="madam du tillait" type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:48012:46"/>
            <pb n="79" facs="tcp:48012:46"/>
            <head>THE HISTORY OF <hi>Madam</hi> Du Tillait, <hi>Written in a Letter to another Lady, who deſired it of a Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman of her Acquaintance.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Madam,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>SInce you were pleaſed to command me to give you an account of Madam <hi>du Til<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lait,</hi> I ſhall obey and relate to you a ſmall part of the Hiſtory of her Life, for if I ſhould endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to give you the whole, it
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:48012:47"/>would take up the reſt of mine.</p>
            <p>Since I am ignorant whether you know her by ſight, I ſhall here ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyn a deſcription of her Perſon.</p>
            <p>She is delicately ſhaped, and of a good ſtature, ſhe has fine but blew Eyes, a very paſſable Complexion (eſpecially for a French Woman) black hair, her Mouth not much too big, and her Teeth pretty even and white, all which toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther would make up a Woman of a very good Mine, and much to be admired, if it were not ſpoiled by an impudent Air, which does ſo raign in her Face, that by the firſt look one may gueſs her to be an abſolute <hi>Meſſalina;</hi> as for her Inclinations they are ſweet and free to that degree that ſhe denies nothing that one can ask her, but thinks it a ſin againſt Nature to deny what is requeſted of her
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:48012:47"/>with a good grace; in fine, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam, ſhe has a thouſand conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Qualities which would infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly have advanced her to the firſt rank of Women, if ſhe had been either at the Courts of the King of <hi>Ethiopia,</hi> or of the Queen of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>She was educated by her Grand-mother, Madam <hi>de la Houſſay,</hi> in whoſe Houſe ſhe had no ſooner come to the fifteenth year of her Age, but ſhe fell deſperately in love with one <hi>Chanteau,</hi> who has been dead now ſome time; he was not a Man of Quality indeed, but a very handſom Fellow, and had a great deal of Wit: This Lady be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at that time very pretty, he perceived with no ſmall joy the good will ſhe bore towards him, &amp; profited ſo well of it that he ſoon obtained of her what ever he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired, but ſcarce was the Flower of
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:48012:48"/>this young Beauty gather'd, but the Fruit appeared, for in ſome time (notwithſtanding all the tricks that were plai'd to hinder it) it came to perfection, about which time ſhe found it neceſſary to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to her Grandmother that ſhe would paſs ſome few days with one of her Aunts a Nun at the Port Royal, under which pretence ſhe went and liv'd at a Midwifes houſe in the <hi>Rue du Four</hi> at <hi>Paris,</hi> where ſhe was brought to Bed of a Daughter, who was taken care of by <hi>Chanteau.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>She was abſent but four days, at the end of which ſhe returned to her Grandmothers houſe, where ſhe kept her Bed the full time, pretending to be ſick of a Feaver, at which time (her Woman Mrs. <hi>du Plais</hi>) has told me, ſhe proteſted ſolemnly ſhe would never return to that ſin ſhe had been ſo ſick in
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:48012:48"/>this Lying-Inn, by reaſon of he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tender Age; but ſcarce was ſhe out of her Bed when ſhe forgot all theſe Vows that were extorted from her by the violence of her pangs, and was with Child again, and was brought to Bed this ſecond time at the ſame Midwifes houſe, but not ſo ſecretly as the firſt, for it is believed her Father knew it well, although he has always pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended himſelf ignorant of it, which was not very likely, conſidering his great haſt of marrying her ſo ſoon after this ſecond Slip, which he did to <hi>Monſieur le Preſident du Tillait,</hi> who after having lived with her ſeveral years, and believed her a Veſtal, found her in Bed with a Gentleman of the Court according to the notice that was given him by his Brother Mr. <hi>de la Cour des Bois,</hi> who was much incenſed with her permitting any other to par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:48012:49"/>of thoſe favours ſhe had af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forded him. The manner of her being ſurprized was thus: He having pretended to go into the Country, came home (contrary to her Expectation) at Night, and found the Gentleman with her, who was forced to run away in his Shirt, and leave his Clothes in the Ladies Chamber, ſince which her Husband has never ſeen her nor owned a Daughter of which his wife went from the time of this Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture, for ſhe was brought to Bed nine months after of her, who now is called (Madam <hi>du Plais</hi>) this Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman who was thus caught, and was then ſo much in Love with her has been ſo conſtant to her, ſince that he has had of her two Sons, one dead and the other who is now his Page, he always thinking him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf the only Perſon in her favour till he was diſabuſed by this acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent,
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:48012:49"/>after which he found him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf far from being in the right, for then ſhe had many others, ſince ſhe has given up her ſelf to all the World.</p>
            <p>The manner of his diſcovering the Ladies having other Gallants, was thus: She had an old Maid called <hi>Richarde,</hi> that was the beſt in the World at entertaining Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce with a dozen Gallants for her Miſtreſs at the ſame time, for ſhe never ſpoke of one to the other, without making each of them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve himſelf to be the ſole fortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate Lover, but ſhe had another who was not ſo ſecret, for upon ſome ſuſpicion the Court Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man had of the Abbot of <hi>Aumont,</hi> ſhe readily confeſſed the truth that he lay with her Miſtreſs, at the knowledge of which, and the ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſing them once together by this Maids contrivance, he was ſo
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:48012:50"/>inraged, that he endeavour'd to run the Abbot through, who hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing put by the thruſt, and cloſed upon him, gave the Lady time to call up help to part them, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding which the Abbot was hurt in the Face and Hand, but as ſoon as he was gone the Gentleman diſcharged his Anger upon the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, and gave her ſo many blows with the flat of his Sword that ſhe lay ſick of it at leaſt a Fortnight or three Weeks, during which time ſhe was forced to keep her Bed; ſince this Affair the Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man never cared for her, but broke with her wholly, notwithſtanding all ſhe could do to appeaſe him.</p>
            <p>After which the Lady having ſo well begun in her young years, was reſolved to finiſh ſo, and aban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doned her ſelf ſo up to Vice, that it was to the three States, the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility, Clergy and Commonality.</p>
            <pb n="87" facs="tcp:48012:50"/>
            <p>Some time after this ſhe retired into the Hoſpital of the <hi>Charonne</hi> in the ſaid Suburbs of Saint <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane,</hi> becauſe of ſome Creditors that proſecuted her very ſeverely, thinking thereby to gain time to pay them.</p>
            <p>While ſhe was in this Covent ſhe made an Acquaintance with a Father Jeſuit, called <hi>Faverolles,</hi> who as I take it, was Director of Conſcience to the Nuns of that Covent, whoſe ingenious Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation was ſo pleaſing to her, that ſhe had many private Conferences mith him, in which the good Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther found ſomething in the Lady that made him hope to gain her Favour, which being no very diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult thing, he ſoon came to the end of his Deſign, which he had no ſooner acquainted her with, but ſhe promiſed him ſatisfaction; ſo that there's nothing wanting now
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:48012:51"/>but opportunity he obtained ſo much of the Lady, that ſhe diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered to him a Grate that ſhe had in her Parlour, which came out when ſhe pleaſed, which as ſoon as the Father heard, he made ſuch uſe of it, that he would not ſtay any longer, but went through the Grate to the Ladies Chamber, who ſeemed not to be diſpleaſed at this Freedom, but agreed ſo well with him that they left the uſe of their Diſcourſe, though not of their Enjoyment of their Pleaſures, which they continued to take ſo long together, that ſhe found her ſelf with Child in a ſmall time, of which being to be delivered, ſhe made a Journey to <hi>Farmontier</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der pretence of ſeeing ſome Nuns of her Kindred there, where hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing been ſome time, ſhe was brought to Bed of a Boy (which dyed ſince at <hi>Somiers,</hi> where he
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:48012:51"/>was at Nurſe) whither, although it was very difficult for Father <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verolles</hi> to lie out of his Covent, He did not fail to go to viſit Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam <hi>du Tillait</hi> at the time of her lying in; from whence as ſoon as he had given order for the nurſing of his little Jeſuit, he came back to <hi>Paris,</hi> whither he was hardly come when he received an order from his Superiour to go to <hi>Ami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ens</hi> (for I know not what Affair) but however having heard there that Madam <hi>du Tillait</hi> was very ill, he left all the buſineſs of his order, and went to her, whom finding much better than he expected, and his buſineſs at <hi>Amiens</hi> not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting him to be long abſent, he returned thither the next after he had recommended her to the care to one <hi>Puard</hi> a Chyrurgion, who had brought her to Bed, and orde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red him to have a great care of
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:48012:52"/>her health, which he did to ſo good effect, that with that and his being a hanſom Fellow, he got ſo far into her favour that he had care of her Pleaſures as well as her Lying-Inn, in which he pleaſed her ſo, that now he was got into the Jeſuits place in his abſence, who when he came back (in four Months time, during which he could not poſſibly quit his buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs) found his Miſtreſs with Child of <hi>Picard.</hi> It did not a little per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plex the Lady to find out how to diſcover the Truth to the good Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, but finding it muſt come out ſoon or late (he never leaving her) ſhe reſolved to break the Ice with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out delaying it further, which ſhe thought it beſt to do in Confeſſion to him, in which ſhe told him all that happened between her and the Chyrurgion, but withal aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red him that it was only to keep
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:48012:52"/>the thing ſecret, however this thing ſo troubled the Father that he had utterly broken with her, had he not known People of his Sort did not always meet with ſuch good Fortunes, wherefore he thought it not convenient to loſe this, and thereupon only made her ſome few reproaches, but ſhe quickly ſhut his mouth, by telling him it was not juſt for him to reproach her for any thing ſhe had told him under the Zeal of Confeſſion: Some time after this they came together to <hi>Paris</hi> where the Father's Amour being known by the Jeſuit, they checked him ſeverely for it, and for the preventing any further communication betwixt them, they ordered him to go to <hi>Moulins,</hi> but inſtead of obeying their order he retired into Madam <hi>du Tillait</hi>'s houſe, of which the Jeſuit not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing informed were more than a
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:48012:53"/>year without knowing what was become of him, till at length they heard he kept houſe with his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved Lady, from whence they got an order from the King to have him brought home to them, which was accordingly executed by an Exempt of the King's Guards, who found him at Madam <hi>du Tillait</hi>'s houſe in Bed with her at ſix of the Clock in the Morning, from whence not having any Clothes on, he was carried immediatly to the Jeſuit, who to puniſh his open and immodeſt behaviour, put him in Pace <hi>(i. e.)</hi> into their Dungeon for ſix Months, during which time the Lady made a ſhift to conſolate her ſelf with abundance of Abbots, who were in Love with her, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt whom there were the Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bot <hi>Fournier Foreas de Treville du Four,</hi> and many others of her Acquaintance, which would take
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:48012:53"/>up too much time to name them, came in ſuch Numbers that her who houſe ſeemed to be the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation Houſe of the Clergy.</p>
            <p>As ſoon as Father <hi>Faverolles</hi> was out of Priſon he left the Jeſuit, and being retired into ſome Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner out of the Jeſuits Knowledge, he obtained by the Intereſt of ſome Perſons of Quality a Diſpenſation for leaving the Jeſuit Habit, and becoming a Secular Prieſt.</p>
            <p>Some time before this he got in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Madam <hi>du Tillait</hi>'s Favour a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, at whoſe houſe there happe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to him a very pleaſant Adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture with Abbot <hi>Fournier,</hi> who then held the firſt place in the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies affections, for after having lived there in ſecret near a Month, he was forced to retire, which hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened thus, the Ladies Woman had at laſt diſcovered to the Abbot that he was in the houſe and promiſed
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:48012:54"/>him to bring him where he ſhould find them together, and ſo he might by threatning the Father, which out of the fear of being caught there the ſecond time might make quitt the Ladies Company, in order to which Deſign ſhe hid him in her Chamber, and told him that her Lady and ſhe always kept a Diſh of their Supper, and carried it to the Father whilſt the Servants were at Supper below, ſhe bad him alſo be ſure, (as ſoon as he ſhould ſee a Candle paſs by ſuch a ſtair-caſe where the Father's Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber was) to come at the ſame time to the Door, where as ſoon as he ſhould knock ſhe would go to the Door, making her Miſtreſs believe ſhe thought it to be another Maid of the Houſe, that knew of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther's being in the houſe; in fine, they ordered their Intrigue ſo well, that it fell out as they deſired.</p>
            <pb n="95" facs="tcp:48012:54"/>
            <p>For the Lady being come home, but at Eleven of the Clock the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther's Supper was not carried to him paſt Eleven, where as ſoon as the Lady and her Maid was with him, the Abbot comes up to them and knocks at the Door, and the Maid opens it to him, who came in and immediately asked Father <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verolles</hi> how he dared be ſo bold as to be at Madam <hi>duTillait</hi>'s houſe af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter he had bin fetched from thence by the King's Expreſs Command, to which the good Father Jeſuit being not of a very patient temper, anſwered ſomewhat angryly, tell<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him, that was not his buſineſs, and therefore he needed not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern himſelf any further in it; but the Lady doubting they would come (as it ſeems they did) to blows, deſired them both to make no more noiſe in her houſe, ſaying to the Abbot, that as for him ſhe
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:48012:55"/>had a better opinion of his Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom than to believe he would make any diſorder in her houſe, and as for the good Father, ſhe doth not doubt but that he being of the Society of <hi>Jeſus,</hi> will have ſo much patience as to let the Affair paſs without any noiſe, but not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding all his precaution and deſire of the Lady, the Father bad the Abbot go out of the Room immediately, at which the Abbot making ſport, he took a Diſh which the Lady had brought him wherein there was a Fricaſſee boyling hot and made the Abbot a Mask with it, in which moment the Abbot alſo took up an Ewer and flung it at his head, after which they fell upon one another and made ſo much noiſe in the Fray, that ſome feuillant Monks (of whom Madam <hi>du Tallait</hi> ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted her houſe) that were ſaying
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:48012:55"/>Mattins, hearing all this buſtle through their Church Windows, which look into her Court, thought there were Thieves in the Houſe, ſo that the Father Procurator of the Covent, who was booted and ſpurred, ready to go to look after ſome buſineſs at a Country Houſe belonging to the Covent, was ſent to her aid and went ſtraight up to the Chamber where he heard the Noiſe, with ſome of her Servants that he had told the reaſon of his coming thither (they having heard nothing of the noiſe before) where having knocked at the door as hard as he could, and no body anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, he was confirmed in his opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that they were Thieves, and that they had killed the Lady, upon which he and the ſervants reſolved to break it open, which the Lady perceiving, thinking ſhe muſt at laſt open it, reſolved to let it be
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:48012:56"/>half open to the Monk (which was better than to be ſeen with Father <hi>Faverolles</hi> by all her ſervants) which ſhe did, but withal com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding her ſervants to be gone, and let the Monk come in alone, which ſhe hoped might make an agreement betwixt theſe two an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry Lovers, which accordingly he did, ſo that they both agreed, but it was in falling out with and vent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all their anger upon the Lady, reproaching her with her ill Life, and other things of that nature, but at length being all agreed, they all three deſired the <hi>Fevillant Monk</hi> to be ſilent and not to diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver this adventure, but he being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirous to gain by this occaſion, told them that the only means for them to be aſſured of his keeping their Secret, was for him to be in a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition that ſhould alſo need their keeping a Secret for him, by which
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:48012:56"/>he made them underſtand, and by other good Reaſons that he would not retire from thence upon any other conditions than enjoying Madam <hi>du Tillait,</hi> which the two o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Lovers at length granted, and went out of the Chamber leaving the Monk with the Lady booted as he was, who not being uſed to ſuch favourable opportunities made very good uſe of this.</p>
            <p>The next morning after this af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fair Father <hi>Faverolles</hi> left Madam <hi>du Tillait</hi>'s Houſe for fear the Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bot ſhould inform the Jeſuit of his being there, and thereby once more be put in <hi>Pace,</hi> but the Lady not being willing to be far off from a man that had ſo many good amo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Qualities, as <hi>Faverolles</hi> had, took a Chamber at a Surgeon's Houſe over againſt the <hi>Sorbon,</hi> where ſhe ſeldom let a day ſlip without viſiting him, which Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bot
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:48012:57"/>
               <hi>Fournier</hi> (who I think was born to be a Scourge to <hi>Faverolles</hi>) knowing by the Ladies Woman, who ſaid her Lady went every day to that Chyrurgeon's Houſe, but ſhe did not know to whom it was ſhe gave the Viſit, for ſhe was always ſent back with the Coach home, how ever this ſoon made him think it to be <hi>Faverolles,</hi> but that he might be certain of it, he reſolved to watch at the Chyrur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geon's Door, which he did one day when the Woman told him her Lady was there, where having ſtaid ſome time he eſpied two little Dogs which Madam <hi>du Til<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lait</hi> carries always with her, which he immediately followed up ſtairs to the Chamber door where their Miſtreſs was (after having done what he could to catch the Dogs before) but he being diſguiſed in a grey Cloak they did not know
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:48012:57"/>him) whither as ſoon as he came one of the Dogs ſcratched at the Door, upon which the Abbot caught him up, and hearkned at the Door, in which moment the Lady having-heard her Dog ſcratch, came to open the Door, which as ſoon as ſhe had done the Abbot ſtept in and told her he having found her Dogs in the Street, had endeavoured to catch them, but they running away from him he had followed them that they might not be loſt, but withal that he was very ſorry he had followed them ſo far as to interrupt her Enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment.</p>
            <p>Notwithſtanding all theſe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences the Father thinking he had done all this to catch him, imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately gave him a box on the car, after which there being no body to part them, they fought ſo heartily that they were forced both at laſt
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:48012:58"/>to make uſe of the Man of the Houſe who was a Chyrurgeon.</p>
            <p>The Abbot threatned the Father ſo much this time alſo that he was forced to leave the Town for fear of further diſcovery, and take a Houſe at <hi>Iſey</hi> a Village near <hi>Paris,</hi> where the Lady viſited him very often, though not without enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining at the ſame time many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Gallants, amongſt whom there was one Mr. <hi>L' Avocat,</hi> a Fellow that has neither Wit nor breeding, but yet a Maſter of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſts of the King's Houſhold, was Chief, as being one of the greateſt Fops ſhe could induce to love her, yet having got ſome money from him, and a pair of white Flanders Coach-Horſes, he had the firſt place in her affections, next him was <hi>Guerin</hi> her Steward, who had a great ſhare of her Favours, and often of her Bed, where being
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:48012:58"/>one Night, there happened a plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant adventure, which was, that three Rivals ſhould meet at a time when it was almoſt impoſſible they ſhould ſee one another, in order to the unfolding of which you muſt know Madam that <hi>L' Avocat</hi> had for Confident one of the Ladies Foot-men, and Abbot <hi>Fournier</hi> one of her Maids.</p>
            <p>The Lady not being diſpleaſed at their catching her, agreeably continues in Bed, they often hid themſelves ſomewhere till ſhe was in Bed, and then came to her which the Abbot doing once in her Maids Chamber, and <hi>L' Avocate</hi> in the Foot-mans, and the Lady happe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to have that Night <hi>Guerin</hi> in her Bed who having been in Bed ſometime, thoſe Lovers alſo that were hid came into her Chamber each of them thinking to be the only one there, but both coming
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:48012:59"/>in at the ſame time, ſhe bad the Steward hide himſelf under the Bed, and asked who was there, to which <hi>L' Avocate</hi> ſaid, it is I Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam, who come to paſs a quarter of an hours time with you, to which ſhe anſwered, truly Sir, it is too late now, not too late, Madam, replied the Abbot, for it has but juſt now ſtruck twelve of the Clock; truly, Sir, replied the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, I took you for <hi>L' Avocate,</hi> and ſo it is truly, ſaid <hi>L' Avocate,</hi> on the other ſide of the Bed, who then came to the Bed-ſide, and flung him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf upon the Bed, ſo as to meet the Abbot (that was by this time got to the other ſide of the Bed) and took him by the hand, whom he asked, when they knew one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, why he that might come at any time to the Lady, being ſo near a Neighbour, ſhould come at that time of the Night, to which the
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:48012:59"/>Abbot, anſwered very angrily that he wondered how he ſhould come thither from his Houſe at the other end of <hi>Paris</hi> ſo late at night, after which they gave one the other ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ill Language, which had come to blows, if they had had any mind to fight, or if the Lady had not promiſed to give them all ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginable ſatisfaction, which agreed upon at laſt amongſt them thus that <hi>L' Avocate</hi> being fartheſt off his Lodgings ſhould be the firſt two hours with the Lady, after which the Abbot ſhould come, and that in the mean time the Abbot ſhould retire into another of the Ladies Chambers. Theſe two being ſatisfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed there remained only poor <hi>Guerin</hi> unſatisfied, who was very ill lodg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed under the Bed in his ſhirt with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out hopes of getting any thing by the Treaty till the Abbot had done with the Lady whom he left at ſix
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:48012:60"/>in the Morning, and gave him his place in the Ladies Bed, where he took his full revenge of them, which was not unwelcome to the Lady; in fine, Loves feaſt was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver better ſolemnized in this world than this night by three Lovers, who all went away with ſo great a ſatisfaction, that they had not the leaſt Jealouſie or Malice left them.</p>
            <p>Here, Madam, I muſt beg your leave to finiſh this ſmall account of Madam <hi>du Tillait,</hi> wherein you will be pleaſed to believe there is nothing of Falſhood, ſince I aſſure you I know of <hi>Faverolles</hi> (who is now my very good Friend, and is ſince fallen out with the Lady) all that happened between him and the Lady whereof I have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trenched the greateſt part, as not being fit for your Ears. As to <hi>Chanteau</hi>'s affairs, I knew it from
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:48012:60"/>the Ladies Woman, who was then with her; and as for that of the Court Gentlemans, it made ſo great a Noiſe in the World, that I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve it is unknown to very few.</p>
            <p>As for that of her Steward, it was related to me by himſelf ſince he came from her, in a Month after which, he was found aſſaſſinated at the Port Saint <hi>Jacques,</hi> but by whom it is not yet known.</p>
            <p>Since it pleaſed you, Madam, to deſire me to diſguiſe nothing in this Relation, I hope you will not be diſpleaſed at the too great Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty I have taken, and that you will believe as a great truth, that I eſteem nothing ſo much in this World as your Self, and all things that have any relation to you.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
